Mazel tov מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Today's Daf Yud דף י. Daf
Yud. It's also the 48th day in the Omer עומר, Omer, the
penultimate day in the Omer עומר, Omer, Erev Erev Shavuot ערב ערב
שבועות. Erev Erev Shavuot. So, if anybody's behind on the Daf Yomi
דף יומי, Daf Yomi, you can catch up on Shavuos שבועות. Shavuos.
All right, we are at the bottom of Daf Tet-Zayin Amud Bet
דף טז עמוד ב. Daf Tet-Zayin Amud Bet. We just got through
like three dappim דפים dappim or so on the whole discussion of
meitav מיטב, meitav, of what form of payment you make when you
owe money for damages, and now really
the rest of the
masecheta מסכתא masecheta focuses—I would say that's like one particular segment that's
a little bit off-topic, you know, and spread beyond just nezek נזק,
nezek, but really now we focus for the next good long while
on the direct question about mamon hamazik ממון המזיק mamon hamazik and
when your property or when you as a person does damage and
under what circumstances you're liable for paying. We dealt with a mishna
משנה mishna that was quite cryptic, as we mentioned the language also
was pretty archaic, seems to be a very old mishna משנה mishna
and had that line at the end repeating the line of the
first mishna משנה mishna of כשהזיק חב המזיק לשלם תשלומי נזק ממיטב
הארץ. Kshe-hizik chav hamazik leshaleim tashlumei nezek mimeitav ha'aretz. When the animals
do damage or the property does damage you have to pay with
the best of the land. And the mishna משנה mishna in particular
framed it as חבתי בשמירתו הכשרתי נזקו. Chavti bishmirato hichsharti nizko.
When I was obligated to watch and presumably I was negligent and
didn't watch, it was
like I had created the damage that would occur. It's like I'd
laid the groundwork for the damage that would occur. So that really
seems to emphasize in terms of this big overarching question about why
are you liable; are you liable for the fact that your animal
did it or are you liable because your negligence brought it about?
The mishna משנה mishna certainly seems to emphasize the latter. It's like
you ultimately brought about the damage. Okay. Anyway the Gemara גמרא Gemara
used that as an opportunity to discuss a different level of negligent,
or maybe that's the wrong way of saying it, but circumstance in
which you're more liable for your ox and for your well than
you are for fire in a case when you gave it over
to a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve-katan. And that was a
debate of Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish exactly what the parameters of that were. We will
see more about that later in about about two weeks. We will
see the much more focused debate of Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and Reish Lakish ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Why should it be
exactly that in a similar circumstance you're more exempt by a fire
than by these other things? Reish Lakish ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
because fire the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan leaves alone and
it basically goes out on its own, but Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan seems to say that even if the fire was more
of a live flame you'd be exempt, and that we're going to
be exploring more later. Okay. Now we move on though with that
background and remembering that difference about the fire that you're more exempt
from that in a parallel case of than you would be in
a parallel case of an ox and a well. We look at
the following braita ברייתא braita that we pick up five lines from
the bottom or six lines from the bottom. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
And again because this mishna משנה mishna that we just read is
this pretty like generic mishna משנה, mishna, you know, sort of pulling
together all of the אבות נזיקין, avot nezikin, כל שחבתי בשמירתו, kol
she-chavti bishmirato,
we have a braita ברייתא braita that might evoke what we did
a few days ago, a type of a comparing and contrasting the
different אבות נזיקין. avot nezikin. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. חומר בשור מבור וחומר בבור משור. Chomer bashor miba-bor ve-chomer
ba-bor mibashor.
There are ways in which shor שור shor here which means the
ox and specifically in this context goring is more stringent than the
well and cases in which the well is more stringent than the
goring. חומר בשור מבור. Chomer bashor mibabor. What's the way in which
the ox is more stringent than the well? שהשור משלם את הכופר.
She-shor meshalem et hakofer. If an ox gores a person and the
person dies as a result and the ox is a מועד, mu'ad,
then it pays כופר. kofer. You pay some atonement payment. And however
if a person falls in a well and dies, you are do
not pay an atonement payment. Okay atonement payment is only when an
ox gores, not when a person kills a person there's no civil
liability, it's not when a person dies in a well, it's only
when an ox gores a person or any of your animals or
whatever kills a person. Okay so that's כופר. kofer. וחייב בשלושים של
עבד. Ve-chayav bishloshim shel eved. And if it kills a slave it
pays the קנס knas of thirty כסף, kesef, thirty שקל. shekel. And
that's not again not true about when your well causes a slave
to die, not true if you cause a slave to die. There
are, you know, some of those cases could be murder but the
point is they're not but they're not a civil payment. נגמר דינו
אסור בהנאה. Nigmar dino asur behana'ah. Also there's a law of a
שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. If it killed somebody and it went through
the process of being judged by a, you know, in front of
a court and it was found to have killed somebody it would
be a שור הנסקל shor haniskal and it would be you couldn't
get any benefit from it even before it was stoned from the
moment that its judgment was passed. Okay and that whole status of
שור הנסקל shor haniskal does not apply to anything else. ודרכו לילך
ולהזיק. Ve-darko leilech ulhazik. So those are the laws that are more
stringent and the circumstances of it, the character of it. characteristics of
it that make it a more weighty category is that it goes
around and creates damage, it's not just things come to it like
the well. מה שאין כן בבור, ma she'ein ken bebor, none of
those things are true by the well. חומר בבור משור, chomer bebor
mishur, but the well is weightier than the ox, שהבור תחילת עשייתו
לנזק. shehabor techilat asiyato lenezek.
A well from the moment it was created was a hazard. Ox
gets born as a cute little calf. Okay, so it's not like
the whole thing from its very identity is a hazard. ומועד מתחילתו,
umuad mitechilato, and even more so in contrasting it to an ox,
say to goring of an ox, because a normal ox is not,
doesn't have a propensity to gore and to damage, whereas a well
from its very beginning has the propensity, right? So that's תחילת עשייתו
לנזק. techilat asiyato lenezek. תחילת עשייתו לנזק techilat asiyato lenezek means its
very identity from its very beginning is that it's a hazard. The
other thing is like whether the damage that it causes is a
likely or not likely occurrence. By a goring of an ox, that
is very unlikely and unexpected and that's why you only pay half
damages. By a well, it's to be anticipated. Okay, but it would
also be anticipated by a שן ורגל, shen veregel, by the walking
or the eating of an ox. Okay, מה שאין כן בשור, ma
she'ein ken beshur, that's not true by a שור. shur. So that's
comparing שור shur to בור. bor. Now we're going to do compare
שור shur to אש. esh. חומר בשור מבאש, chomer beshur mibe'esh, שור
shur is weightier than an אש. esh. חומר באש משור, chomer be'esh
mibeshur, and an אש esh is weightier than a שור. shur. חומר
בשור מבאש, chomer beshur mibe'esh, in what way is the שור shur
weightier than the fire? ששור משלם כופר וחייב בשלושים של עבד, sheshur
meshalem kofer vechayav bishloshim sheleved, like we said, this is always going
to be what's weightier about קרן, keren, are all of these civil
payments, monetary payments in the case of death. So if it kills
a person who is a free man, you pay a כופר kofer
payment, if it kills a slave, you pay שלושים של עבד, shloshim
sheleved, and that there's the story of שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. All
of those things are only true by קרן, keren, so that's going
to be our stock way in which קרן keren is weightier than
other things. Okay, ודינו אסור בהנאה, vedino assur behana'ah, and now here's
a new one though, which refers back to what we discussed yesterday,
מסרו לחרש שוטה וקטן חייב. mesaro lacheresh shoteh vekatan chayav. If you
gave an ox to a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan to
watch, let's assume like the first answer of the Gemara that it
was bound up, nevertheless, it's you would be liable because it would
naturally more undo its... מועד, muad, right? No, not well we'll talk
about that, that's an interesting question, but not necessarily, I mean the
other one you'd be maybe fifty percent, there's actually a very interesting
question whether the level of care you have to give for a
שור תם shur tam might even be ironically higher than a מועד.
muad. So let's hold off on that. Okay, but anyway, giving it
to a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan is not sufficient because
even if it is bound, it is likely that it will struggle
free of its binds. Anyway, so חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan
is not sufficient to be ensuring that it will remain protected. So
you're liable, חייב. chayav. מה שאין כן באש, ma she'ein ken be'esh,
as opposed to an אש, esh, an אש esh we said for
whatever reason, maybe because as an ember it'll die out and the
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan don't have won't make it worse,
they won't make it better but they won't make it worse, that's
acceptable. So none of those things are the true by שור shur
true by אש, esh, even in that last case the חרש שוטה
וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan would be פטור. patur. It did not give
the difference of דרכו לילך ולהזיק darko leilech ulehazik because an אש
esh is also דרכו לילך ולהזיק. darko leilech ulehazik. Okay, חומר באש
משור, chomer be'esh mibeshur, now in what ways is an אש esh
weightier than a שור? shur? שאש מועדת מתחילתה, she'esh muedet mitechilatah, מה
שאין כן בשור. ma she'ein ken beshur. So that's also when we
compare to קרן, keren, the thing that's going to be the other
thing is going to be weightier than קרן keren is that the
other thing has a propensity to do damage. A fire, the first
time, it's considered likely and you pay full, which is not true
מה שאין כן בשור. ma she'ein ken beshur. Okay, so that's comparing
שור shur to אש esh and שור shur to בור bor and
what makes שור shur weightier is always going to be these payments
when people die. Okay, and the fact that it's a שור הנסקל.
shor haniskal. Now, חומר באש מבור, chomer be'esh mibebor, okay, so you
understand what we did,
right? We did שור בור shur bor and we did שור אש,
shur esh, okay, and what makes this weightier is always going to
be כופר kofer and שלושים של עבד shloshim sheleved
and שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. Okay, and we did all those things.
And what makes these weightier, well the obvious thing that makes any
of these weightier is מועד מתחילתו. muad mitechilato. That's always going to
be the obvious part, plus some other stuff. Okay, like that אש
esh is going to be, אש esh is the שמירה shemirah of
a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan works. So we did those,
so the only thing we haven't compared yet of these three is
בור bor to אש, esh, right? Okay, so, okay,
חומר באש מבור וחומר בבור מבאש. chomer be'esh mibebor vechomer bebor mibe'esh.
חומר בבור מבאש, chomer bebor mibe'esh, שתחילת עשייתו לנזק. shetechilat asiyato lenezek.
Okay, a well is from the very outset a hazard. I mean,
a fire you could say could spread or whatever, but it's not
seen as like you put a well in the middle of רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, that's danger hazard, okay, as opposed to like a
fire that you lit in your own property. תחילת עשייתו לנזק. techilat
asiyato lenezek. מסרו לחרש שוטה וקטן חייב. mesaro lacheresh shoteh vekatan chayav.
And again, a well you are חייב chayav when you give it
to a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh vekatan because as the way
we explained yesterday, even if it's covered. the cover can break and
you need to give it to somebody responsible to make sure that's
not going to happen. מה שאין כן באש, Mah she-ein ken be-eish,
by an אש, eish, it's not from its outset like a hazard,
okay? That's what in its character makes it weaker, and in terms
of and in terms of its הלכה halacha what makes it more
lenient is you're פטור patur when you give a גחלת gachelet to
a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh ve-katan.
חומר באש מבור, Chomer be-eish mibor, now in what way is an
אש eish weightier? שאש דרכה לילך ולהזיק ומועדת לאכול בין דבר הראוי
לה בין דבר שאינו ראוי לה מה שאין כן בבור. She-eish darchah
leilech u'lehazik u'mu'edet le'echol bein davar hara'ui lah bein davar she'eino ra'ui
lah mah she'ein ken be-vor. Because a fire goes out and creates
damage, right, as opposed to the thing coming to it? That's in
terms of what its character makes it more weightier. What in terms
of its הלכה halacha makes it more weightier? That it has a
propensity to destroy, to consume, whether something's fit for it or unfit
for it. Now what does that mean? That's so far the first
really cryptic phrase we've hit. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
דבר שאינו ראוי לה מאי? Davar she'eino ra'ui lah mai? What is
a thing that's not fit for it that an אש eish is
liable and a בור bor is פטור? patur? Okay, that would be
the הלכה halacha in which an אש eish is weightier.
דבר שאינו ראוי לה מה שאין כן בבור. Davar she'eino ra'ui lah
mah she'ein ken be-vor. I'm sorry, did I
skip a line? Okay, I'm
good. וליתני חומר בשור מבור. U'litnei chomer be-shor mi-bor. Now one minute,
let's go back to שור shor and בור bor and there's another
difference. Okay? What's the other difference between שור shor and בור bor
before we unpack what
ראוי לה ra'ui lah means? ששור חייב בו את הכלים מה שאין
כן בבור. She-shor chayav bo es hakeilim mah she'ein ken be-vor. So
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: So what do we have? So
the בור, bor, it's weightier because of תחלת עשייתו. techilas asiyaso.
And
how else is it weightier? Because of the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh ve-katan case. Okay, this is weightier because of דרכו לילך. darco
leilech. And the הלכה halacha that it's weightier is דבר שאינו ראוי
לה. davar she'eino ra'ui lah. So we're going to have to figure
out what דבר שאינו ראוי לה davar she'eino ra'ui lah means, that
we're going to have to get back to. Okay. But now the
גמרא Gemara is saying there's other things that we forgot. What else
should we have listed? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: וליתני
חומר בשור מבור ששור חייב בו את הכלים מה שאין כן בבור.
U'litnei chomer be-shor mi-bor she-shor chayav bo es hakeilim mah she'ein ken
be-vor. By a שור, shor, for שור shor gores כלים keilim or
steps on כלים keilim or whatever, you'd be חייב. chayav. מה שאין
כן בבור, Mah she'ein ken be-vor, but by a בור, bor, right,
the famous דרשה drasha is, we've referred to this before, but it's
important to know it, right,
it says ונפל שמה שור או חמור. venafal shamah shor o chamor.
And the
דרשה drasha is: שור ולא אדם חמור ולא כלים.
Shor velo adam, chamor
velo keilim. Now, שור ולא אדם shor velo adam is confusing because
שור ולא אדם shor velo adam means if a person is injured...
if a person dies, excuse me. If a person is injured, you
actually would pay injury. Makes sense. I mean, that's a huge hazard,
falling into a well. How could you not be liable for that?
Okay, well we'll see that, fine.
But anyway, the שור ולא אדם shor velo adam just exempts a
person by death, okay? Death of a person, you're פטור. patur. And
that's what we've been saying, there's no payments for death. But this
is the more common one to be focusing on, which is you're
only חייב chayav by חמור chamor and not by vessels. So why
don't you say a שור shor is חייב chayav in כלים keilim
and a בור bor is פטור? patur? Oh, that's not a חומר.
chomer. That... Okay, so the שור shor is more חמור chamur because
it's חייב chayav in כלים, keilim, okay, and a בור bor is
פטור patur in כלים. keilim. Why didn't we list that? So the
גמרא Gemara says: וליתני חומר בשור מבור ששור חייב בו את הכלים
מה שאין כן בבור. U'litnei chomer be-shor mi-bor she-shor chayav bo es
hakeilim mah she'ein ken be-vor. הא מני רבי יהודה היא. Ha mani
Rabbi Yehuda hi. This is רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דמחייב על נזקי
כלים בבור. De-michayev al nizkei keilim be-vor. That he says that actually,
he doesn't hold of this whole דרשה drasha and he holds that
if vessels get damaged in a בור, bor, you're חייב. chayav. So
the גמרא Gemara says, one minute: אי רבי יהודה אימא סיפא. Ei
Rabbi Yehuda eima seifa. Let's look at the end because now we're
going to use this to figure out what this line meant by
אש. eish. Okay? חומר באש מבור שאש דרכה לילך ולהזיק ומועדת לאכול
בין דבר הראוי לה בין דבר שאינו ראוי לה מה שאין כן
בבור. Chomer be-eish mibor she-eish darchah leilech u'lehazik u'mu'edet le'echol bein davar
hara'ui lah bein davar she'eino ra'ui lah mah she'ein ken be-vor. This
cryptic line that a fire eats things that it's not fit for,
which is not the case by the בור. bor. So what does
this line
mean? שאינו ראוי לה. She'eino ra'ui lah. So דבר הראוי לה מאי
ניהו? Davar hara'ui lah mai nihu? What's normally fit for fire? עצים,
Eitzim, you know, normal fuel, wood. דבר שאינו ראוי לה, Davar she'eino
ra'ui lah, what's not fit for fire? מאי ניהו? Mai nihu? כלים,
Keilim, vessels, because it doesn't mean that a fire won't damage vessels,
but it means it doesn't normally... you don't normally burn your vessels
in a fire. So if that's true, מה שאין כן בבור, mah
she'ein ken be-vor, so we think that this line that אש eish
you're חייב chayav by unfit things and you're פטור patur by בור,
bor, so we assume this means כלים. keilim. If a fire burns
כלים, keilim, you're חייב, chayav, but if a בור bor damages כלים,
keilim, you're פטור. patur. Okay? So that would be a great example.
All right, so if this is talking exactly about contrasting כלים, keilim,
then this should be contrasting the כלים keilim as well. You're חייב
chayav in כלים keilim here and you're not חייב chayav there, the
same way that's what it's saying by the fire. חייב Chayav in
כלים keilim by the fire, פטור patur in the בור. bor. So
the גמרא Gemara says: So if... Yehudah, but if it's רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehudah is the reason we didn't mention כלים keilim above by
the שור בור shor bor comparison, הא אמרת ha amart מחייב היה
רבי יהודה mechayev hayah Rebbe Yehudah on נזקי כלים nizkei keilim בבור.
bebor. So you just said that this whole ברייתא braita is going
like רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehudah, and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehudah says that
you are חייב chayav in כלים, keilim, so that's why we don't
have it here. So if everything is חייב chayav in כלים keilim
and a בור bor is חייב chayav in כלים, keilim, what is
this thing about אש esh that's weightier? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא לרבנן היא. ella lerabbanan hee.
Fine, you're right. It's not רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehudah, it is the
רבנן. Rabbanan. And this line here means כלים. keilim.
This line means כלים. keilim. You're חייב chayav in כלים keilim by
אש esh and you're פטור pattur in בור. bor. So you know
what? It should have said here: you're חייב chayav in כלים. keilim.
That would have been another contrast. So why did it not? Okay,
אלא לרבנן ותני ושייר. ella lerabbanan vetannei veshayar. You know what? Because
it's an abbreviated list, it didn't list everything. All right, you're right,
there's another difference, but it's an incomplete list. So now the גמרא
Gemara says what it always says when it says it's
an incomplete list: מאי שייר דהאי שייר? mai shayar dehai shayar? What
else did it leave off? Because you're not going to give a
list of differences and say every single difference except one. You might
as well then give a complete list. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
cannot accept the idea that it's a list where just one thing
was left off. If you're going to tell me it's an incomplete
list, you've got to show me that at least two things were
left off. Okay, so what else was left
off? שייר טמון. shayer tamun. Ah, that's a very good other thing
to leave off. One of the other exemptions is a little חזרה,
chazarah, if you remember, do you remember the גמרא Gemara there on
like I think it was ד עמוד ב daled amud bet or
ה עמוד ב hey amud bet which says: so if you have
a big generic obligation for the ארבע אבות נזיקין, arba avos nezikin,
why did you need four categories? And it says because every category
has its own special laws. Okay, do you remember that? שן ורגל
shein veregel you're פטור pattur ברשות הרבים. birshus harabbim. בור bor you're
פטור pattur בכלים. bekeilim. אש esh you're פטור pattur בדברים הטמונים, bidevarim
hamitmanim, things that are buried, that are hidden. Okay, so this is
a little חזרה chazarah of those. What are the special laws of
each category? So the גמרא Gemara says here's another difference. Okay, שור
shor is also weightier than אש. esh. How is שור shor weightier
than אש? esh? What's another way in which שור shor is weightier
than אש? esh? Is טמון. tamun. If a שור shor gores something
that is buried in a haystack, okay, or walks on something that's
buried in a haystack, you're חייב, chayav, whereas if a fire consumes
something that is buried in a haystack, you're פטור. pattur. Okay, so
actually we left off some of those areas. We'll worry about it
when we get to it. But right now what we said is
we left off those areas where you have special exemptions: בור bor
is exempt from כלים, keilim, אש esh is exempt from טמון. tamun.
It could have listed those as ways in which שור shor is
weightier and it did not. So it's an incomplete list. All right,
so שייר טמון. shayer tamun. איבעית אימא, eebai eima, if you want
I could say, so that's one answer. It's רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehudah,
this here means כלים, keilim, that's the way אש esh is weightier
than בור, bor, and it didn't mention those things here, it's an
incomplete list.
Why doesn't it ask what it mentioned, things that it didn't mention?
It never asks that. איבעית אימא לעולם רבי יהודה. eebai eima leolam
Rebbe Yehudah. It is רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehudah. So כלים keilim you
are חייב. chayav. All right, by a בור. bor. So if that's
true, forget the fact that it's an incomplete list. Okay, you're חייב
chayav by כלים keilim by בור. bor. And that's why it did
not mention כלים keilim up here, because you are חייב. chayav. So
if that's true, what's this thing that אש esh is more liable
for than בור? bor? Right? It's no longer כלים. keilim. So what
is this thing that אש esh is more liable for? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: לעולם רבי יהודה ודבר שאינו ראוי לו. leolam
Rebbe Yehudah vedavar she'aino rauee lo. So what's דבר שאינו ראוי davar
she'aino rauee that you're חייב chayav for in אש esh and not
בור? bor? לאו לאתויי כלים, lav attuyei keilim, it's not coming to
include כלים, keilim, אלא לאתויי לחיכה דנירו וסיכסוכה דאבניו. ella attuyei likhucha
d'niro vesikhsukha d'avnav. What happens if the fire burns
your like fallow field and scorched your rocks? Okay, that's אינו ראוי.
aino rauee. Now there's two questions about that. Number question is: why
is it called אינו ראוי? aino rauee? This happened last time we
read it, right? People said like, I don't know, like classic damage
by fire is smoke damage, why is that not considered to be
ראוי? rauee? All right. And the other question is: how is that
contrasted to בור? bor? What would be the parallel to בור bor
that you would be exempt that you're חייב chayav by fire? Everybody
hear the two questions? Okay, so question number one is why is
that considered to be אינו ראוי. aino rauee. So תוספות Tosafos says,
if you look at the תוספות לחיכה דנירו, Tosafos likhucha d'niro, okay,
תוספות Tosafos says, well תוספות Tosafos answers both questions. I'll read תוספות
Tosafos inside in a minute. Let me just first of all focus
on: what's the מה שאין כן בבור? mah she'ein kein bebor? So
תוספות Tosafos says it sounds like from a later רש"י Rashi that
מה שאין כן בבור mah she'ein kein bebor is: there's no way
you're going to get your fallow field to be damaged by a
well. Try to get a field to fall into a well. Okay,
so now that's a little absurd, תוספות Tosafos says. Why? So why
not say a house? You're no way you're going to get your
house to fall into a well. There's lots of things that are
not going to fall into a well. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos says
we're not obviously comparing something that's possible to something that's impossible. That's
not a basis of comparison like what is the liability in certain
situations. So תוספות Tosafos says: no, here's the point. The point
is...
So if
you have a בור bor that's nine טפחים, tefachim, it's not considered
fit to kill and an animal falls in it and dies, what's
the הלכה? halacha?
An animal falls in a nine טפח tefach בור bor and it
dies, what's the הלכה? halacha?
You would be חייב? chayiv? No, I mean you wouldn't be? You'd
be פטור. patur. You'd be פטור. patur.
Okay, so that shows you that if a well does damage that
should not have been anticipated, you're פטור. patur. And not the fact
that we say a nine טפח tefach well is only liable for
damages and not for death means that if an animal dies in
a nine טפח tefach well you're פטור, patur, which means you are
exempt if it did damage that was not normally damage that it
would cause. Yeah, if an animal dies in a nine טפח tefach
well you're פטור. patur. So you are not liable for damage that
would not normally be done by that well, that could not have
been anticipated that could have been done by that well. And that's
in contrast to fire because fire, even if it damages something that
you wouldn't have anticipated, you're liable. Now, why is burning a fallow
field something you wouldn't have anticipated? So if you look at תוספות
Tosfos you can tell me if you understand the answer or not.
Look at the bottom of תוספות Tosfos לכיכך. lichachah. תוספות Tosfos says
like five lines from the bottom, אלא יש לומר לכיכך, ela yesh
lomar lichachah, look at that word לכיכך, lichachah, okay, לכיכך נירות דחייב
אף על פי שאין רגילות שתזיק אש ניר ואבנים כלל. lichachah nirot
d'chayev af al pi she'ein regilut shetazik esh nir v'avanim klal.
Meaning, it's not like a fire won't spread to a fallow field,
but what is the likelihood, you know, that a rock really gets
damage, gets damaged by a fire? Now I don't know, like what
does that mean? Like what value do rocks have? Is that the
point? Is the point that normally a fire just, you know, doesn't
even doesn't even burn the rock, it just burns the stuff around
it? How about a fallow field? I understand that there's no standing
grain for it to burn and I guess that's the point. The
fallow field doesn't have any like, it just has dirt, right? It
doesn't have any normal fuel. So maybe it's unlikely what's getting it
to spread into a dirt field? I mean I don't know, that's
a good question. If you have just, I have no idea, if
you have just a big, like a like a sandlot, okay, and
you've got a fire, will it spread into the sandlot? Will it
spread into like a place of just like dirt? If there's nothing
for it to burn or will it burn the dirt? I don't
know. Does anybody know the answer to that?
I think I think what you said is right, it wouldn't burn.
It wouldn't, it would like burn grass and it would burn trees.
Right, but it
could still be fallow, right?
If you had a lot of
dry grass in the summer, if you had dead grass.
So but I think the point about the rock and the fallow
field, fallow field, right, is
Fallow field doesn't mean it's completely empty? Yes it means. No it
means like you're not growing any like produce there?
Oh you mean that it would like have wild stuff that might
be growing.
Yes and in the in the summer months you have to mow
your
lawn so that there's not really high dead grass because that's more
of a fire hazard than.
Okay, but if you have a field that you use for growing
wheat, right, and once every few years you just let it lay
fallow, right, so there probably will be some random growth from accidentally
dropped seeds or other types of things. But I guess the point
is that it's very unlikely that the fire will do any serious
damage to a rock or fallow field because there's nothing for it
to catch onto. And even so, if it does do that, you're
חייב. chayiv. Okay, so for תוספות Tosfos that's the contrast. דבר שאינו
ראוי לו davar she'eino rauy lo is, you know, rocks and whatever,
fallow fields, okay, where it's unlikely,
okay, unlikely. And that's and that's contrasted to בור bor because בור
bor you're not חייב chayiv for unlikely. If an animal dies in
a nine טפח tefach בור, bor, you're going to be exempt. Okay,
so now we've got פשט pshat and we're not dealing with כלים,
keilim, it could be like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you're even
חייב chayiv in כלים keilim for a בור. bor. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues. מתקי לה רב אשי. Matki leh Rav Ashi. So
רב אשי Rav Ashi has another question or we'll see it ties
into this one. דאיכא חומר בשור מבבור שהשור חייב בו שור פסולי
המוקדשין מה שאין כן בבור. de'ika chomer bashor mibibor shehashor chayav bo
shor psulei hamukdashim ma she'ein kein babibor.
So this is a very obscure הלכה. halacha. If a if an
ox gores, I had an ox that I sanctified as a קרבן
korban and then it got a מום mum and then I transferred
the קדושה kedushah and I brought some other animal as a קרבן.
korban. So this ox that once was קדוש kadosh is called פסולי
המוקדשין, psulei hamukdashim, invalidated הקדש. hekdesh. Now it's still my my property
and I can still שחט shecht it and eat it and the
whole thing, but there are some limits, okay? I can't I can't
shear it, I can't, you know, work it or whatever.
You can't like sell it in.
Exactly, we'll have the same thing. But anyway I have some limits,
okay, and if it dies I can't get הנאה hana'ah from it
if I didn't שחט shecht it, if I שחט shecht it I
can eat it, whatever, anyway. So there the הלכה halacha is that
it's basically considered mine, so if your ox gores my ox of
פסולי המוקדשין, psulei hamukdashim, you're חייב. chayiv. But there's a very strange
הלכה halacha that if that ox falls into a well, the owner
of the well is exempt, מה שאין כן בבור. ma she'ein kein
babibor. So why do we give that? That's such an interesting נפקא
מינא, nafka mina, it happens every day. So anyway the גמרא Gemara
says, so we'll see later what that's based on, how we know.
you're exempt by a בור, bor, but that is a הלכה. halacha.
אי אמרת בשלמא רבנן היא, Iy amrat bishlama Rabbanan hi, now if
you say like you said before that it's the רבנן Rabbanan about
כלים, keilim, so we said it was an incomplete list, so אידי
דשייר הכא שייר נמי הכא, aidi deshayer hacha shayer nami hacha, we
already said we didn't discuss the כלים keilim נפקא מינה nafka mina
and we didn't discuss טמון tamun and now we also don't discuss
שור פסולי מוקדשים. shor psulei mukdashim. There are a lot of things
we left off the list. אלא אי אמרת רבי יהודה, Ella iy
amrat Rabbi Yehuda, but if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda not only does he reject the exemption of כלים keilim
by a בור, bor, you know what else רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
exempts? No, that he holds by. He rejects the exemption of טמון
tamun by אש. eish. So we had one or the other. So
we have nothing, so according to him it's not an abbreviated list,
right? So the only thing now that we left off was this
שור פסולי מוקדשים. shor psulei mukdashim. So that's not acceptable. You can't
have a list that has everything but one. מאי שייר דהאי שייר?
Mai shayer de-hai shayer? שייר דש בנירה. Shayer dash binira. Ah, here's
what it would leave off. What happens if an ox goes ahead
and plows a fallow field? Okay, now that, first
of all, it just decided it was bored, so anyway רש״י Rashi
says you know these oxen are trained to plow, so somehow you
had left some type of I guess the apparatus hooked up to
it and it walked to the fallow field and it plowed it,
which presumably damages the fallow field. You want to leave it better?
I don't know, did it? I don't know, trust me I ain't
no farmer. I have no idea. Now the other funny thing is
that until now if you asked me what would that be considered?
Quick, which category would you put that in? I accidentally left
my harness, whatever, my plow hooked up to my cow and it
walked over and it plowed your field that was fallow. I think
it would be רגל regel too, right? It's just a natural type
of thing it does. רש״י Rashi for some reason says it's קרן
keren and כוונתו להזיק. kavanato lehazik. I have no idea why, and
at the same moment that רש״י Rashi says it does because it's
habituated into doing it. Anyway, so why is that, now what's that
contrasted to? So רש״י Rashi says well that's contrasted to the well
because for the same thing he said before, a field can't fall
into a well. So that's another thing it left off. When an
ox damages a field and you don't have that by a well
because a field can't fall into a well. Very strange. Anyway, that's
the other thing it left off. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says no, אי משום דש בנירה לאו שייר
הוא, iy mishum dash binira lav shayer hu, then no you can't,
that's not a good answer, you didn't leave that off the list.
דתנא שכן דרכו לילך ולהזיק, De-tana she-ken darko leilech u-lehazik,
that's just a natural
consequence that the ox goes out and does damage whereas by the
well things have to come to it. So included is that difference
is that the ox will damage things that are, can't move, whereas
a well can only damage things that can move or that can
be moved to it. So basically what we said is that according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda this doesn't work because according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda there's one thing that was left off the list,
פסולי מוקדשים, psulei mukdashim, and we can't accept a list that's complete
except for one thing. But according to רבנן Rabbanan it works well,
there's a lot of things left off the list: טמון tamun and
כלים keilim and פסולי מוקדשים. psulei mukdashim. Yes, question?
I was going to ask you, so the מסקנא maskana is just
for רבנן.
Rabbanan. Yeah, the מסקנא maskana is that it doesn't work according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, correct. Okay, moving on.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We said that... Did we try to answer
it according to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
Yeah, but we rejected the answer because we said that's already included
in the differences that we list. If it's just a difference of
an ox can go and damage things that can't move or be
moved, that's included in the difference between דרכו לילך ולהזיק. darko leilech
u-lehazik. Right, and then we're left with
the question, so therefore it's
not רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay, הכשרתי במקצת נזקו.
Hichsharti be-miktzat nizko. Now the second cryptic line of the משנה Mishna
is not only when I have been negligent in the full watching
of it did I lay the groundwork and prepare the damage that
would occur, but even if I only was negligent in part, הכשרתי
במקצת, hichsharti be-miktzat, what is it? הכשרתי במקצת נזקו חבתי בתשלומי נזקו
כהכשר כל
נזקו.
Hichsharti be-miktzat nizko chavti be-tashlumei nizko ke-hachshar
kol nizko.
Even if it's like I only sort of laid the groundwork for
some of the damage, I'm liable for all of the damage. That's
a very suggestive statement. You want to guess? Go.
Like if you have a בור bor that's nine טפחים tefachim and
he brings it to ten טפחים. tefachim. Now I didn't dig the
whole בור, bor, so like I sort of filled it and then...
filled it or continued to dig it?
That's what I mean, I deepened it. I deepened it, yeah. Then
I'm חייב chayav if the שור shor falls in and dies, whereas
it wouldn't have been before.
Okay, so you sure you never learned this גמרא Gemara before?
Okay, so it's buried in your memory somewhere. Let's look at the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. I just figured it out. Yeah,
exactly. Of all the million possible million possibilities you got the exact
one the גמרא Gemara is talking about. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הכשרתי
במקצת נזקו חבתי בתשלומי נזקו כהכשר כל נזקו. Hichsharti be-miktzat nizko chavti
be-tashlumei nizko ke-hachshar kol nizko. כיצד? Keitzad? What's the case that you
only did a little bit of damage, you prepared a little of
the damage and now you're חייב chayav for all the damage? החופר
בור תשעה, Ha-chofer bor tisha,
so somebody ראובן Reuven dug a בור bor nine טפחים tefachim and
he's חייב chayav for נזק nezek but not for death as we
said, ובא אחר, u-va acher, then שמעון Shimon came והשלימו לעשרה ve-hishlimo
le-asara
and dug it the tenth טפח. tefach. So and now if an
animal dies in the well there's no question that it's only שמעון
Shimon's responsibility, because ראובן Reuven did not do anything that could bring
about death. Okay, but the חידוש chiddush is that let's say now
an animal is damaged in the well, who you think is liable?
Reasonably you would think let ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon split it.
Because ראובן Reuven already did what ראובן Reuven did would have brought
about damage. So no, that's going to be the big חידוש. chiddush.
Okay, האחרון חייב ha'acharon chayav the last one is חייב chayav even
for נזק. nezek. So it's not such a big חידוש chiddush to
say the last one is חייב chayav for death because although it's
true that ראובן Reuven sort of laid the, did the first nine
טפחים, tefachim, the last one did the thing that made it a
death trap. Okay? And therefore he's of course it's his, death is
his responsibility. But in terms of damage, even though he only a
little bit contributed to the damage, he's liable for the full damage.
ודלא כרבי, v'd'lo k'Rabbi, not like רבי, Rabbi, דתניא d'tanya we taught
like in a ברייתא, braita, החופר בור תשעה hachofer bor tisha ובא
אחר והשלימו לעשרה, uba acher v'hishlimo l'asara, ראובן Reuven dug nine and
שמעון Shimon came and did the tenth, אחרון חייב לנזיקין, acharon chayav
l'nezikin,
the last one has to, אחרון חייב, acharon chayav, the last one
is חייב. chayav. רבי אומר Rabbi omer אחר אחרון למיתה, achar acharon
l'misa, no, no, I agree the last one has to pay for
death, ואחר שניהם לנזיקין, v'achar shneihem l'nezikin, but if it's damage they're
both liable. So clearly when the תנא קמא tanna kamma holds that
even the that the last one is liable even just for the
נזק. nezek. Now why is that? Okay, so if you take תוספות
Tosafot quotes a refers to a גמרא Gemara that quotes a פסוק
pasuk because logically you should say they should split it if it's
just נזק. nezek. So look at תוספות, Tosafot, אחרון חייב, acharon chayav,
תוספות Tosafot says, גם הנזיקין, gam hanezikin, ראשון פטור מכולם, rishon patur
mikulam, okay, and he's exempt from death and from damage. ופרק הפרה
מפרש טעמא u'perek hapara mefaresh ta'ama דכתיב d'chsiv כי יכרה איש בור
ki yichre ish bor אחד ולא שנים, echad v'lo shnayim, one person
digs, לחיובא בתר עשיה. l'chiyuva batar asiya. That's coming to say that
even if two people did it, there are cases where only one
person is חייב. chayav. ולא קאמר v'lo ka'amar דהמיתה דיליה d'hamisa diley
הוא דקעביד שם מיתה. hu d'ka'avid shem misa. Now it's only when
the last one made it into a בור bor fit to be
killed, meaning the last one transformed its identity. Let me give you
another example. Michael dug a בור bor of eight, and I added
another טפח. tefach. Or he dug a בור bor four and I
added four טפחים. tefachim. An animal came and got damaged. Who do
you think is liable that case? The answer is we're both liable.
We both, you made a בור bor of נזק, nezek, and I
participated and also it was still a בור bor of נזק nezek
and I just made it more possible to damage. In that case
we're both liable. The difference is when I basically turned it into
a different type of a בור, bor, not just made it more
possible to damage, but I made it qualitatively different. You made a
בור bor of נזק, nezek, I transformed it into a death trap.
I transformed it into a בור bor of מיתה. misa. So because
I transformed it, it now is completely identified as my בור, bor,
not your בור. bor. Okay, so is that clear the difference here
is only because the first guy made נזק nezek and the second
guy changed its identity into a בור bor of מיתה. misa. If
the first guy, let's say you did ten טפחים tefachim and I
added ten טפחים, tefachim, or you did four and I added four,
we would we would both be liable. Okay, so that's the חידוש.
chiddush. There are times when you only did a little, but because
you've transformed its identity, it becomes all yours and you're liable for
full נזק. nezek. And that's going from nine to ten.
Yes. Just trying to figure out like in Gemara's view like are
we equally liable at four and four?
I can understand that, but what
about four and one?
Right, so that's a good question. So let's hold off on that.
Right, like according to רבי, Rabbi, nine and ten are they equally
liable? What about eight and nine, would they be equally liable? So
those are good questions and part of those questions, by the way,
okay here's a nice little נפקא מינה nafka mina by the way
to just to give you a way of thinking about the answer
to Michael's question, which could depend on the conceptual models we've been
dealing with. Here let's see if you can figure this one out.
I'm not saying this is the right answer, but this is the
way I would go. We said that there's two ways of thinking
about these things. Is it because my negligence brought it about, or
is it because it's my thing and because it's my thing I'm
liable for the damage that it does? So let's say you dug
eight and I dug a ninth טפח. tefach. Or you dug one
and I dug eight more, what either case. So if you use
the model of saying negligence, would you say and fault etc., how
you would say we would split it? Equally or proportionally?
You're both at fault.
Yes, but if I dug eight and he only dug one, I
would think that I have more contributory negligence to the damage than
he does. Right, I would think that you would divide it proportionally,
not equally. Right? You don't think so?
Depending on if it's one and eight or eight and one.
Well, okay, you mean the order might matter or something. Right, but
as but the point is if you're thinking about negligence, you would
think in terms of different types of distribution, right? You would try
to assess that. But if you're thinking about it's my בור bor
and I'm liable for my בור bor because it's not because I
was negligent and I was at fault. It's my בור bor and
I have to pay for what my בור bor does. So whose
בור bor is this? It's both of our בורות. borot. We're like
partners in the בור. bor. So in that case, to me, I
would more incline to be saying that if you use that model,
you split it equally. Once we both participated in it, it's we
both own it like we both own a cow. Now you could
say let's say Michael owns twenty percent of my cow and I
own eighty percent of a cow and it damages, do we split
the damage twenty-eighty, or do we split it fifty-fifty? So you can
could end- He's only one person. Right, תוספות Tosfos just quoted that.
Right, so that's to share a בור bor joint ownership.
No,
because that's
only because of the end of the פסוק pasuk about המית יהיה
לו hamess yehi lo when you've made it into a בור מיתה.
bor mitah. We limit it to that type of a case. Okay.
Right, but a בור נזק bor nezek can be shared. Right? So
you do see though right it's interesting about how do you think
about different degrees of ownership and are you thinking about it in
terms of liable for something you own or liable because of your
fault and your negligence. All right, anyway.
So in the case of a שור shor do we not say
that you split it?
That's all those are going to be סוגיות sugyas coming up. We're
going to have a lot of fun, okay? Can't answer everything in
one day, Michael. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay.
רב
פפא אמר, Rav
Pappa amar, Rav Pappa says, למיתה דברי הכל. lemisa divrei hakol. No,
actually, it could be going like רבי. Rebbe. It could be he
went from nine to ten and it's saying that the last one
is חייב chayav for death and then it goes even according to
רבי. Rebbe. Now that's less of a חידוש chiddush because of course
the last one is חייב chayav for death. It's a little bit
of a חידוש chiddush because the nine sort of laid the groundwork
for the death. But anyway, so that would be a case. I
just did one טפח tefach and I'm חייב chayav fully חייב chayav
for the death. Okay, so that's a less of a חידוש chiddush
but that way it would be going even according to רבי. Rebbe.
איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, לימא דלא כרבי. leima d'lo keRebbe. Some say
we started by saying, oh, let's say our ברייתא brayisa our משנה
mishna is not like רבי Rebbe because it has every... the last
one is חייב chayav for everything. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Pappa, למיתה דברי הכל. lemisa divrei hakol. No, the last... same point,
just where we started from. No, actually the משנה mishna could be
talking about death and it's going even according to רבי. Rebbe. The
last guy, even though he only added one טפח, tefach, is חייב
chayav fully for death. For נזיקין, nezikin, that's debated. Okay. מתקיף לה
רב זירא. maskif lah Rav Zeira. So רב זירא Rav Zeira challenges.
ותו ליכא? v'su leka?
So who do we...
who do we פסקן paskin like? Whatever, we'll see... we haven't פסקן.
paskined. We'll worry about it later when we get to it. It's
coming up in a, you know, whatever, 40 days. Okay. מתקיף לה
רבי זירא. maskif lah Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asks. The
nature of the first פרק perek is like the sort of first
סוגיא sugya where we're referring to a lot of things that get
developed much more in the later דפים. dapim. So don't expect a
full treatment of some of these things. מתקיף לה רבי זירא. maskif
lah Rabbi Zeira. Now Rav Zeira asks, ותו ליכא? v'su leka? Are
you telling me there's no other cases where you just did a
little and you're liable for everything? I will show you other cases
like that. זה איכא. za ika. How about the following? Now this
is interesting. As רשי Rashi points out, this is not a ברייתא.
brayisa. This is just a thought issue, like a, you know, it's
just a סברא. svara. It's like, I can imagine other cases that
would also the last guy would be liable for everything even though
he only did a little. What case? Let's talk... let's think about
it. Let's say, מסר שור לחמישה בני אדם. masar shor l'chamisha bnei
adam. I gave my ox to five people to watch together. I
need a... this ox is a very dangerous ox, you all have
to watch it together. ופשע בו אחד מהן u'pasha bo echad mehen
and one of them was negligent. והזיק v'hizik and because that one
guy was negligent, although the four guys were doing what they should
have been doing, it was able to go out and escape and
to damage. חייב, chayav, he's חייב chayav even though he only was
one-fifth of not watching. Now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. That's
not a חידוש. chiddush. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי
לימא דבלאו איהו לא הוי מינטר. ee lema debila ihu lo havei
mintar. If without him it wouldn't... it was... it was necessary, right,
to make sure it was watched, without him only four people would
not have been sufficient to watch the ox. פשיטא. pshita. Of course
he's negligent and he's 100% negligent. דקא עביד, de-ka-avid, he did it.
His negligence made the watch... made the ox unwatched. Okay. אלא דבלאו
איהו נמי מינטר. ella debila ihu nami mintar. Must be that actually
no, I was just doing redundancy. Actually this ox could be watched
by any one person, but I was so concerned that I made
five people obligated to watch it. I was just being redundant. But
technically it could have been watched by anybody. So if that's true,
מה קא עביד? ma ka avid? So what did I do? So
the one guy's not considered פשיעה? pshia? Okay, because by him leaving
and going off the job, he really did not expose it to
damage. The damage would still be considered unexpected because the ox was
being watched regardless. So, oh, so that's not a נפקא מינה nafkamina
because it's not true. It's either obvious or it's not true. So,
מתקיף לה רב ששת. maskif lah Rav Sheshet. So רב ששת Rav
Sheshet says, I'll give you another case that maybe we should be
thinking about.
Wait, so we...
so we didn't answer that? Yeah, well we did answer it. The
reason that we're not listing that as a case of the משנה
mishna is because either it's obvious in one scenario or not true
in the other scenario. Okay, מתקיף לה רב ששת. maskif lah Rav
Sheshet. רב ששת Rav Sheshet asks. האיכא מרבה בחבילא. ha'ika marbe b'chavila.
If you added a bundle of wood to your friend's fire and
the fire spread. He made the fire, but you added the wood
and it spread. Then it's my fault? Well, yeah. היכי דמי? heichi
dami? What's the case? It's going to be the same point. Either
it's obvious or it's not true. אי דבלאו איהו לא אזלה. ee
debila ihu lo azla.
If the fire wouldn't have spread without you adding
the
bundle of wood...
פשיטא. pshita. Of course you're negligent. It's your fire. You spread it.
So it's not you only מקצת נזקו. miktzas nizko. That was כל
נזקו. kol nizko. אלא דבלאו איהו אזלה. ella debila ihu azla. Okay
but okay we'll say it a different way. Without you it would
have spread. In any way was going to spread the fire. So
if that's true, מאי קא עביד, mai ka avid, what are you
doing? Now תוספות Tosafot says it does not mean that you are
exempt. Michael made a fire that's spreading, and if I do nothing
that fire is going to damage and Michael will be liable. I
throw more gasoline on the fire. Okay? So am I like so
does that mean now how do you read the גמרא Gemara מאי
קא עביד? mai ka avid? You read the גמרא Gemara like I'm
totally off the hook? It was going to happen anyway, so what
I made bigger flames? That's I think how the פשט pshat of
the גמרא Gemara would be. But תוספות Tosafot doesn't like that. תוספות
Tosafot says, really? You could actually make it a bigger fire and
be exempt just 'cause it would have happened anyway? So look at
תוספות. Tosafot. Very interesting תוספות. Tosafot. בכל שמעתין צריך לומר מאי קא
עביד טפי מאחריני. B'chol sh'matin tzarich lomar mai ka avid tfei me'achrinei.
What am I doing more? Why should I be liable everything just
'cause I added the bundle of wood? וישלמו כל אחד חלקו. V'yishalmu
kol echad chelko.
Here everybody should pay their portion. Does their portion mean equal portion?
Does it mean proportionally? Also not clear. Now, ואין לומר דליפטר. v'ein
lomar d'lifter. Now you don't say דליפטר, d'lifter, I should be exempt.
The fire was going to spread. I didn't add to the damage
just because I added to the fire.
דתניא בפרק הפרה אחד החופר בור ליוד ובא אחר והשלימו לעשרים ובא
אחר והשלימו
לשלושים כולם חייבים אף על גב דבלאו איהו הוה מיתה. D'tanya b'perek
hapara echad hachofer bor l'yud u'ba acher v'hishlimo l'esrim u'ba acher v'hishlimo
l'shloshim kulam chayavin af al gav d'belo ihu hava meisa. That, you
know, one guy did ten, the other guy added ten, the other
guy made it thirty, they all pay, even though the animal would
have died anyway. So if that's true here, even if it would
have burnt anyway, I added to the fire, it's also my fire.
מיהו Mihu says תוספות, Tosafot, בזה צריך לדקדק. b'zeh tzarich l'dakdek. But
you know what? תוספות Tosafot says it's clearly not so clear because
you have to think about the specifics. וכי בשביל שהשליך איש עץ
בתוך אש גדולה. V'chi bishvil she'hishlich ish etz b'toch esh gedola.
Michael had a huge bonfire, I took my toothpick and I threw
it into the fire, okay? יתחייב? הלא דמי לאחד שחופר בור יוד
ובא אחר והשלימו ליוד אלף. Yitchayev? Halo damei l'echad she'chofer bor yud
u'ba acher v'hishlimo l'yud aleph.
Right? So that's that's trivial. So how much would I have to
do to add to the fire to make it equally my fire?
Okay, if I can add to the בור bor by digging an
equal ten טפחים tfachim and it's equally my בור, bor, what would
I have to do to make it equally my fire? By the
way, you could also say maybe the models matter. Maybe by בור
bor the model is who is the owner of the בור. bor.
And if I dig ten and Michael digs ten, we're both owners
of the בור. bor. By the fire, maybe the issue is less
who is the owner of the fire as whose actions brought about
the damage. And since Michael's actions would have brought it about anyway,
my adding some extra wood was not bringing about the damage, the
damage was going to happen. So you see the models you use—is
it ownership or negligence—might change based on בור bor versus אש esh
etc. So now you're seeing why those models matter. It's not necessarily
and you know and how do we exactly distribute liability in those
cases?
So what is תוספות Tosafot saying
in that case?
In the case of—let's say you did add a toothpick.
תוספות Tosafot says he's clearly got to be exempt, okay, entirely.
But then what תוספות Tosafot says is, is that but then he
says, but then I don't know, when is the threshold that when
you do become חייב? chayev? I am, yeah. It doesn't seem to
be the תוספות—or Tosafot
like it seems to me like there is a space to not
read תוספות Tosafot that way.
You mean there's a question about proportional?
Yeah, like because תוספות Tosafot is saying, okay, you know, חופר בור
יוד ובא אחר והשלימו ליוד אלף, chofer bor yud u'ba acher v'hishlimo
l'yud aleph, that person should not be liable for equal, but maybe
should be liable for...
Yeah, it's not—I think that's true. תוספות Tosafot is a little vague.
תוספות Tosafot could have the word הכל. hacol. He could have said
וכי בשביל שהשליך איש עץ בתוך אש גדולה יתחייב הכל. v'chi bishvil
she'hishlich ish etz b'toch esh gedola yitchayev hacol. He says יתחייב, yitchayev,
which sounds like, look, this is totally your fire because I threw
a stick in it, it becomes all of a sudden I become
a part participant in your—so I think that those are like the
questions to ask, right? Maybe there are three stages. There's something I
do that's seen as trivial. There's something I do that's seen as
some degree contributory, right? So anyway, all of those תוספות Tosafot doesn't
know the answer. He leaves those as open questions, right? And as
I'm saying, I think the question of the model, is it a
model of ownership or a model of negligence, could also factor into
how you think about this. But the גמרא Gemara says, Michael had
a fire and it was going to destroy, burn, and I added
some wood, but it didn't burn more than it would have, but
I added wood, would I really be חייב? chayev? And the question
is does that mean would I be חייב chayev everything? Certainly not.
Would I be חייב chayev anything? That's less clear. Yes.
But fire specifically in this case, because the pit they gave is
a specific amount, nine or ten טפחים. tfachim. Right. In the fire,
even if nothing was added, there's no way to determine how far
it...
Exactly. Exactly. And that's why thinking about thinking about ownership of a
well, is that's why it's an easier model of ownership. It's like—it
stays in its place. You actually people do own wells, right, that
you're digging for storage or for whatever. It stays you create, right?
And therefore, like you could say, I made this amount, you made
that amount, so we're both sort of owners, whereas by fire I
agree it's like—it's harder to define it quantitatively. And the more question
you would ask is whose acts brought about the damage in the
end? Who like... who was who had contributory negligence here? Right. Exactly.
Exactly. And there's a lot of different factors. Right. I agree. Okay,
yeah.
Wait, one other thought is that this is super relevant in contemporary
life because like when in studies of airplane crashes, there's actually a
lot of articles about this one, like if it's a series of
negligent actions, like there's so much redundancy that you would require like
multiple negligencies to create an airplane crash. But so then like who's
חייב? chayav?
So we're going to get to that. So let's keep on reading,
because we've got some really interesting cases coming up. אלא בלאו איהו
אזלא. Ela bilav ihu azla. So, okay, מה קעביד? ma ka'avid? What
do you do then? Meaning what do you do to be חייב
chayav everything or what do you do to be חייב chayav anything?
Okay, so it can't be that case, because that case is again
either obvious that you'd be חייב chayav everything or you wouldn't be
חייב chayav everything. So מתקיף לה רב פפא. maskif lah Rav Papa.
רב פפא Rav Papa said, I got a ברייתא, braisa, not just
a thought idea. I got a ברייתא. braisa. חמישה שישבו על ספסל
אחד, Hamisha sheyashvu al safsal echad, five people sat on a bench,
ולא שברוהו, velo shivruh,
and it didn't break. ובא אחד וישב עליו ושברוהו, Uva echad veyashav
alav veshivruh, and one guy came and sat on it and because
exactly, he was guy number six, it broke. האחרון חייב, Ha'acharon chayav,
the last one is חייב. chayav. ואמר רב פפא, Ve'amar Rav Papa,
now this is very
interesting, רב פפא Rav Papa said, כגון פפא בר אבא, Kegon Papa
bar Abba, if it's like this guy called פפא בר אבא Papa
bar Abba who apparently was a very weighty gentleman, and he says
that's and he was so weighty that he caused it to break.
Now the question is why did he have to say that? Why
didn't he just say the bench could support five people and not
six people? But anyway, let's just read a little bit more in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? So
there we see it's only the last guy. That's exactly our case
where five guys on it anyway, it's only the last guy and
the last guy is חייב chayav everything. So okay, that's our idea,
the last guy did a little bit and he's חייב chayav everything.
So the גמרא Gemara says what's the case? אי לימא דבלאו איהו
לא אתבר, Iy leima debilav ihu lo itbar, if without him it
wouldn't break, it could support five people and not six people, so
פשיטא, peshita, obviously you sat on it, you know, you exceeded the
weight limit of the bench, you're חייב. chayav. אלא דבלאו איהו נמי
אתבר. ela debilav ihu nami itbar.
Okay, actually, with five people it would have broken anyway, the weight
limit was already exceeded. So מה קעביד? ma ka'avid? So what are
you doing? Either meaning you should be exempt, it would have happened
anyway, or you're certainly not חייב chayav everything, you're just contributory. סוף
אה okay, therefore there's really no scenario where you're חייב chayav. everything.
Okay, either it's obvious because it wouldn't have happened anyway, or it's
not true. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but it's a
ברייתא. braisa. סוף סוף מתניתיא היכי מיתרצא? sof sof masnisa heichi metartza?
So what did what do you need the ברייתא braisa to teach
you? If they're saying it's either it's obvious or not true, what
is the ברייתא braisa teaching me? No, לא צריכא, lo tzricha, here's
the case the ברייתא braisa is teaching me something, okay? דבלאו איהו
הוה אתבר בתרי שעי והשתא אתבר בחדא שעה. Debilav ihu hava itbar
bitrei sha'ei vehashta itbar bechada sha'a. That actually the weight limit was
exceeded, it would have broken had they kept on sitting on it
for the next two hours, but because this guy, sixth guy sat
on it, it broke faster, broke within an hour. And therefore in
that case there's a חידוש chiddush because you could say everybody's weight,
the first five people who were sitting on it were already doing
something wrong. They were exceeding the weight limit, right? Now by the
way, I just want to pause for a moment and say, even
if the first five people were not doing anything wrong, they were
not exceeding the weight limit and the sixth guy came and exceeded
it, you might say, okay, but you five, you should get up
at that stage, you should realize the weight limit is exceeded. But
the bunch says no, that's not their
responsibility. What they were doing was totally okay and therefore even though
now the circumstances have changed, we put all of the responsibility of
rectifying the situation on the last guy that sat on it. Do
you see or hear that? Even though now anybody could stand up,
but it's all the last guy's responsibility. But if the first five
guys were exceeding the weight limit, they were already doing something wrong
and they had to get up. And this last sixth guy sits
down, so you could say now everybody should be getting up, everybody
was doing something wrong. And nevertheless we say the last guy is
חייב. chayav. Because since he is the one that it speeding it
up, he's considered to be the primary responsible party, even though the
first five guys were there first, right? So that is definitely a
חידוש. chiddush. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says והשתא
דאתבר בחדא שעה vehashta de'itbar bechada sha'a דאמרי ליה, de'ameri lei, they
can say to him, אילו לאו את הוינן יתבינן טותי פורתא וקיימן.
ilu lav at haveinan yasvinan tutei purta vekaiman. Yeah, maybe were we
doing something wrong that we were exceeding the weight limit? Yes. But
we would have gotten up before the time was out, when before
any before you know, we'd have gotten up while it was still
safe to get up before it started breaking. Because you came, you
made it happen sooner and ultimately it's your נזק, nezek, because it
happened within this hour, and within this hour had we just been
here, nothing would have happened. So maybe we were doing something wrong,
but nothing would have happened during this hour and it only happened
because of you, you're the מזיק, mazik, not us. It's an interesting
way of thinking about it, right? ולימא להו, Vilayma lehu, let him
say back to them, one minute guys, אילו לאו אתון בדידי לא
הוה אתבר. ilu lav atun bididi lo hava itbar. If you weren't
sitting with me, it wouldn't have broken. So you're already doing something
wrong, we were all sitting there together, so when it broke Broke,
during that first hour, we were all breaking it. I wasn't just
the one who was breaking it. So the גמרא gemara seems to
say: You know what? That actually is a good answer. And you're
right, the גמרא gemara reverses itself. It actually they would all be
liable even though they could have gotten in that first hour by
themselves it wouldn't have broken. Once they started by doing something wrong,
they're all participatory and they're all liable.
Meaning that it can't hold it can't hold five people.
It cannot hold five people for more than... for more than an
hour, for more than two hours. So, but nevertheless, since you're sitting
on it in circumstances in which, now you could say I'm not
doing anything wrong, I'm sitting on it and I will make sure
to get up before the time limit. But the גמרא gemara understands
not that way. You're sitting on it in a way that it
could break under certain circumstances. Therefore, you are it's not like you
are totally not responsible for what's going to happen here. Okay, you
have to pay attention to the fact that your sitting might be
causing it to break. And therefore, when this other guy comes and
you're not getting up, you're also responsible for what happens.
It's almost like it's breaking a little bit every moment.
It's something like that. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says צריכא, tzricha,
so here's the case where the last guy is fully liable and
it's not obvious, it's not like nothing would have happened without him.
דהכי דסמך בהו תבר, dehachi desamach behu tavar,
so now completely gives a different case. Actually, the way רש"י Rashi
says it is, I'm not sitting on the bench. You know what
I'm doing? I am saying, "Hey, Michael, how's everything going?" and I'm
putting pressure down here, and Michael is not able to stand up.
And because Michael can't stand up, it breaks because of Michael's weight.
But you get it? So it's breaking because of Michael's weight because
I am holding you down, not even pushing you, the bigger חידוש
chiddush I'm just holding you down. I am preventing Michael from getting
up, and it breaks because of Michael's weight. Okay. So the גמרא
gemara says, obvious? No, it's not obvious. מהו דתימא כחו לאו כגופו
דמי, mahu de-teima kocho lav kegufey dami, your energy is not like
your body, קא משמע לן דכחו כגופו דמי. kamashma lan dekocho kegufey
dami. Now, obviously, in a normal case I would think כחו כגופו
דמי, kocho kegufey dami, I take a stone and I throw it
through a window, that's כחו כגופו. kocho kegufey. Here's though a bigger
חידוש. chiddush. Because here, if you think about it, it's your body
weight that is causing the bench to break.
Not necessarily, you're pushing me down.
I am not pushing you down. I am keeping you from getting
up. Okay? So it's not really my weight that's causing the bench
to break, okay, but it is somehow seen, you know, that that
that that is I am through Michael, right, I am exerting Michael's
weight on the bench. It's sort of how it is seen. And
especially since Michael's an agent or whatever, you well you could just
say, you know, Michael broke it, I was a גרמא grama that
I prevented Michael, so I think there is a חידוש chiddush here,
yeah.
Without me pushing down, Michael's weight would break the bench?
Oh,
yeah, but he would have gotten up. I mean, the way I'm
reading it, the way I'm reading it is that it says סמך,
samach, I'm reading it that it's not because I added weight, it's
just because I prevented Michael from getting up. Let me see yeah,
if
I'm holding him down.
What does רש"י Rashi say?
Hold on, where's the רש"י? Rashi? לעולם דבלאו
הכי לא
הוי מיתבר כלל.
le'olam de-bal'av
ilu lo
havi mitbar klal. פשיטא?
לא צריכא דלא ישב עליו אלא עמד על רגליו ונשמך. pshita? lo
tzaricha delo yashav alav ela amad al raglav venishmach.
Oh,
so you mean it sounds like from
רש"י Rashi but look at the next רש"י. Rashi. סמך בהו נשמך
עליהם ולא יכלו לעמוד. samach behu nishmach aleihem velo yachlu la'amod.
Yeah, it's not clear from רש"י. Rashi. The first one sounds a
little bit like I added weight. Okay, if I added weight, it's
less of a חידוש. chiddush. Right, then it's clearly כוח. koach. But
if I didn't add weight, I just prevented Michael from standing up,
that is a more of a חידוש, chiddush, you know. Maybe more
of a חידוש chiddush you don't think it's true, that might be.
You're pushing with force and not the weight.
Yeah, the force right, but is force but כוחו kocho is like
it's the energy, like I like my energy is in the rock
and the rock goes, right? And this case, it would sort of
yeah. I mean,
so you're saying that כוחו kocho sounds like I am adding weight?
Or you're sort of like force.
Right, I'm pushing. The pushing force, not just the preventing force. Right,
I agree. I guess the reason I was trying to limit it
to the preventing, A is because it's more of a חידוש. chiddush.
Although, it's so much more of a חידוש chiddush you could say
maybe it's not true. So I don't know, it's a good question.
I have to explore that more. Okay, but that's the case. It's
less interesting than we thought much less interesting than we thought before,
I would say well, if it's my version, it's a little more
interesting, but basically it's interesting because it's not as much that five
plus one and different people are doing it and you are the
last guy and even though they were also doing it, it's a
different story. It's just I am, you know, using somebody's body to
do something and I am חייב.
And again, just as a case where it would have broken, you're
saying at some point.
Well, maybe, or although maybe it's only because I added force, then
maybe not. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says ותו ליכא, vetu leka,
let's try one more case. Let's just do a little bit more.
No, קא משמע
לן כחו כגופו דמי.
kamashma
lan kocho kegufey dami.
We didn't do that. קא משמע לן כחו כגופו דמי. kamashma lan
kocho kegufey dami. דהיכא דגופו תבר כחו נמי תבר. deheicha degufey tavar
kocho nami tavar.
That wherever your body would have broken, so your כוח koach also
broke. So it's not exactly clear what those words are adding. But
anyway, because of your כוח koach you're liable the same way you're
liable if your body. Okay, ותו ליכא *V'tu leika*, let's just get
to the end of the narrow lines. והאי איכא *V'hai ika*, what
about this case? הדתניא *Ha d'tanya*, הכהו עשרה בני אדם בעשרה מקלות
*Hika'u asarah b'nei adam b'asarah maklot*, בין בבת אחת בין בזה אחר
זה *Bein b'vas achas bein b'zeh achar zeh*, ומת *U'met*, כולם פטורים
*Kulam pturim*. So ten people beat somebody with sticks either at the
same time or as one after the other. It was sort of
like, what was that, Murder on the Orient Express. Okay, actually that's
a little different. That's they
all did a full act of מיתה *misa*. Here they all did
a partial act of מיתה *misa*. They're all exempt, because nobody contributed
and nobody was fully liable for the death.
Now רבי אומר
*Rebbi omer*, okay let's take a look. רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר
בזה אחר זה האחרון חייב *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beseira omer b'zeh achar
zeh ha'acharon chayav*. If it were sequential, then it was the last
guy, because everybody else beat him to within an inch of his
life and the last guy beat out that last inch. He was
the guy that killed him. Makes a lot of sense, מפני שקירב
מיתתו *mipnei shekeirev misaso*, because he brought about the death. So according
to רבי *Rebbi*, that would be a case where the last guy
did only a, he didn't do anything quantitatively more than everybody else,
but because he did the last piece, he was the actual guy
that killed him. קירב מיתתו *Keirev misaso*.
Like ten people kill someone and nothing? What? What happens to those
ten?
Yeah, I mean there's a lot of cases where people get out.
I tie a guy before a lion and the lion eats him
up. I mean there's a lot of cases of גרם נזק *gram
nezek* where there's ways that we deal with it without, all right,
you know what, we're moving on. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא *Gemara*
says, so that would be a case according to רבי *Rebbi*, בקטלא
לא קא מיירי *b'ktala lo ka mairy*. We're not dealing with the
death penalty. This is a מסכת *masechet* about נזיקין *nezikin*, about damages.
Okay, ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'is eima*, if you want I could say דפלוגתא
לא קא מיירי *d'pulgta lo ka mairy*. We're not dealing with a
debate. That's רבי *Rebbi* against the חכמים *Chachamim*, it would be making
it going according to רבי *Rebbi*. גמרא *Gemara* says, ולא ואוקימנא דלא
כרבי *v'lo va'ukimna d'lo k'Rebbi*? But one minute, we said, what did
we say the משנה *mishna* meant? When you dug the tenth טפח
*tefach* of the בור *bor* and you became liable fully, including נזק
*nezek*, and that was against רבי *Rebbi*. רבי *Rebbi* said the נזק
*nezek* would be equal. So we did say it's relating to a
matter of the debate. So the גמרא *Gemara* says now, דלא כרבי
כרבנן מוקמינן *d'lo k'Rebbi k'rabanan mukminan*. No, no, we're okay to have
a debate if the משנה *mishna* is going like the majority position.
So the משנה *mishna* would go like the רבנן *rabanan* against רבי
*Rebbi* and say the guy who dug the tenth טפח *tefach* is
חייב *chayav* for everything of the בור *bor*, the מיתה *misa* and
the נזק *nezek*. כרבי יהודה בן בתירה ולא כרבנן *K'Rebbi Yehuda ben
Beseira v'lo k'rabanan*, but to go like a minority position of רבי
יהודה בן בתירה *Rebbi Yehuda ben Beseira* that says you're חייב *chayav*
for the death and not the רבנן *rabanan* who say everybody's exempt
because they're all equal, לא מוקמינן *lo mukminan*, we're not going to
have it go like a minority position. Okay, but this is a
really fascinating גמרא *Gemara* about this question of, as Jacob was saying,
like lots of cases of contributory negligence and is it the last
person that does it, who's considered to be the primary person, when
is everybody equally liable? Those are cases that keep on coming up
in different forms throughout the מסכת *masechet*.
Okay.